Niles Rowland ● 5050 SE 40th Ave. Apt 3 ● Dania Beach, FL 33314

954-588-6693 • niles.d.rowland@gmail.com • http://think-knot.com

Summary of Qualifications

Expert qualifications in system administration, web application design, e-commerce, and search engine optimization with an extensive background in the following broad-based competencies:

System Administration Programming Database Design/Administration
Web Site Design Internet Marketing E-Commerce

- Proven ability to discover and implement software solutions for a wide variety business applications
- Demonstrated talent to apply existing knowledge base for problem solution
- Recognized capability to quickly learn and adapt new technologies

Commonly used technologies and techniques:

LAMP CakePHP	PHP Zend	OOP Codelgniter	MySQL Drupal	Agile Practices Joomla	Unit Testing Mambo	Scrum Smarty
Javascript	Jquery	Ajax	CSS	HTML	Test Driven Development	
Git	Subversion	Apache	Nginx	MVC	Laravel	Jira
Vagrant	Composer	Bootstran	Node.IS			

Professional Experience

Senior PHP Developer

Lennar Homes Fort Lauderdale, FL 2017 – 2018

- Maintain and upgrade PHP library designed to generate contracts in CRM On Demand and send to Docusign for required signatures.
- Maintain and upgrade PHP library designed to generate contracts in Salesforce and send to Docusign for required signatures.

Senior PHP Developer

Taylor and Francis Group

Boca Raton, FL

2014 - 2016

- Maintain and update high traffic web application written using PHP/Bootstrap/Javascript front-end based on the CodeIgniter framework.
- Maintain and update high traffic web application written using PHP/Bootstrap/Javascript front-end based on the Laravel framework.
- Create/maintain/update composer packages allowing the CodeIgniter application front-end to make the SOAP calls
 necessary to query the common core Java API.
- Create/maintain/update composer packages allowing the Laravel application front-end to make the SOAP calls necessary to query the common core Java API

Senior PHP Developer

Real Local Pages, LLC.

Plantation, FL

2012 - 2013

- Maintain and update Business-to-Business application written in PHP and Javascript built on the CakePHP 1.3 and Jquery frameworks using MySQL database for data storage. This application and database served multiple B2B websites.
- Creation and implementation of user interfaces for numerous websites from mockups.
- Developed and implemented strategy to migrate the above application and database to new hosting service without service interruption.
- Developed automated systems to reduce the number of personnel required to maintain the application.
- Developed and implemented initial organization-wide strategy for software version control using git.
- Design and develop Web 2.0 B2B social media application built on CakePHP 2.4 and Jquery.
- Maintain and administer dual machine RHEL system consisting of MySQL database server and Nginx web server

Senior CakePHP Developer

2010 - 2011

Zumba Fitness, LLC.

Hollywood, FL

- Develop software with the CakePHP framework using best programming practices as applied to the latest MVC paradigm and PHP Object Oriented Programming.
- All work was done in a team environment with the code bases being maintained in Git and Subversion repositories using JIRA to track tasks.
- Accomplishments include:
 - Creation of a CakePHP plugin to facilitate Role Based Access Control (RBAC)
 - Creation of a CakePHP plugin to allow for the creation and redemption of coupons to be applied on any of the site shopping carts or stores. Coupons could be restricted to a certain store, product, or role. Coupons could be a set amount discounted, a percentage of the total discounted, or free shipping.
 - Creation of a CakePHP helper to apply dynamic validation rules depending on the location of the user.

Senior Software Architect

Cake Development Corporation

Las Vegas, NV

- Develop software in the CakePHP framework using best programming practices as applied to the latest MVC paradigm and PHP Object Oriented Programming
- All work was performed remotely with team members maintaining close and immediate contact via IRC and Skype allowing members to be physically located across 4 continents.
- The code bases were maintained both in Subversion and Git repositories with tracking systems to list bugs, enhancements, etc. that required work.
- Accomplishments include:
 - Creation of a CakePHP plugin for OpenId according to the OpenId 1.1 specifications allowing for both consumer and identity provider. The specifications make extensive use of the Diffie-Hellman key exchange cryptographic protocol. The plugin is licensed under the MIT license.
 - Extensive work creating reusable code for social networking applications

Program Design and Development/System Administration/Internet Marketing The Neters Group Fort Lauderdale, FL 2001 – 2008

- Design/develop interactive commercial websites used to promote and sell products and services using Linux/ Apache/MySQL/Perl/PHP (LAMP) technology. Many of the sites were built on MVC frameworks utilizing AJAX techniques.
- Conceived/designed and developed a system of powerful web-based applications used to administer/maintain and
 create HTML formatted emails along with the associated web site using PHP/Perl/MySQL/HTML/Photoshop.
 The site's purpose was to attract members to a double opt-in mailing list which was then used for targeted email
 marketing. This system also included the data storage and retrieval mechanisms required to analyze the effectiveness of the marketing.
- Optimize websites for search engine effectiveness.
- Installation/configuration of Linux/Windows operating systems; installation/configuration web servers; installation/configuration of SQL servers.
- Designed and created quality control procedures for activating new clients exchanging information between various data sources via XML/WDDX.
- Created system documentation using SGML converting it to various output formats using JADE
- Provided administration and consultation for various SOHO networks and systems.
- Responsible for content, implementation, and design of various web sites used to increase company web visibility.
- Developed strategies and promotions designed to increase web traffic from various sources including search engines, printed materials, and bulk emails
- Designed/installed/configured bulk email system capable of sending over 3 million emails/day.
- Installed and configured Linux Fedora and SSL/PHP capable Apache web server on numerous machines

Educational Background

Associate in Arts (Emphasis on Electronics and Computer Science)

1987

Olympic College, Bremerton, WA

Computer Science Studies

1989 - 1993

University of California at Riverside

Major Areas of study:

- Mathematics through multi variable calculus
- Structured programming using Pascal, C, and C++
- Theory of algorithms and data structures
- 80x86 assembly language programming
- Computer modeling and simulation
- Theory of automata and computer design

Military Experience

United States Navv

1977-1987

(EM1/E-6 Nuclear Qualified)

- Division Leading Petty Officer in charge of all shipboard electrical maintenance and repair
- Responsibilities included electric plant watchstander training and qualification
- Accepted honorable discharge in October 1987 to pursue other career options

2008 - 2010